TOM ARRA

1525 HILLCREST ROAD DOWNERS GROVE, IL 60516 TARRA3@GMAIL.COM (708) 269-0956

Passionate product manager experienced in directing multiple development teams utilizing a broad base of software development and technology knowledge to build quality products resulting in enhanced company performance and customer satisfaction. Experienced in developing products and teams from the ground up as well as rebuilding stale and struggling products.

### **EXPERIENCE**

## **Senior Product Owner**

BMW Technology Corporation, Chicago, Illinois

October 2016 – Present

# MyBMW/MINI Application

- Doubled size of development team to 9 developers and 1 automation engineer to increase product output based on business demand.
- Worked directly with development and architecture to establish the use of Flutter within BMW for fast and reliable updates across mobile OS platforms (iOS & Android) simultaneously.
- Had ownership of core features from the engineering and product side including Login, Account Create, and Vehicle Mapping.
- Completed initial launch of a brand-new code base and application in 6 markets around the world with no customer/production incidents during the launch phase, with a gain of over new 35,000 users in 7 days.

### <u>Aftersales</u>

- Led overall product planning and coordination for Aftersales features in the BMW Connected app for multiple teams
  with multiple Area Product Owners. Features include Service/Recall Alerts, Dealer Search, and Online Appointment
  Booking.
- Grew the Aftersales group from 3 to 7 teams through rebalancing and staff expansion of 17 people.
- Established new processes to handle the expansion of teams and features including a new feature pipeline and feature change review in order to facilitate faster release cycles.
- Drove feature releases without application dependencies in order to deliver new features and bug fixes to customers faster than other divisions.

# Android

- Started new development team and backlog from scratch to develop the BMW Connected for Android product.
- Launched the first version of BMW Connected for Android. Continued to drive the product development for our Android application through version 5.0. Saw a 1.5-star rating increase over the course of these releases.
- Transitioned Android product work to a new Product Owner in order to move into a Lead Product Owner role for the Aftersales integration within the BMW Connected service.

# **Product Owner**

BMW Technology Corporation, Chicago, Illinois

November 2014 – October 2016

- Part of initial product management team for the new BMW Technology Corporation office in Chicago, IL.
- Led 2 teams of approximately 6 engineers each during the development of the new BMW Connected application for iOS.
- Designed and ran BMW's first external beta test with 1,000 users. Gathered valuable feedback from real users that helped shape the new BMW Connected application.
- Drove design and development teams for the BMW Connected debut at CES 2016. Attended CES as BMW Technology Expert.
- Served as release manager for iOS. Included setting up metadata delivery process for fast and easy App Store updates.

### **Product Owner**

**Microsoft,** Chicago, Illinois April 2014 – November 2014

- Focused on bringing Microsoft Services to the 100 Million Monthly Users' of the Xpress Browser.
- Drove backlog for one development team.
- Defined requirements and led team through development of new browser landing page content utilizing the MSN Weather API.
- Led definition, development, and deployment of OneDrive integration with the Xpress Browser for Asha Devices.
- Represented and evangelized the Xpress Browser team during company wide and external events including trade shows.
- Ran technical training sessions for large groups (30+).

### **Product Owner**

Nokia (Acquired by Microsoft), Itasca, Illinois

May 2013 – April 2014

- Recruited to the Product Owner position for the Nokia Xpress for Windows Phone product after organization changes.
- Led the redevelopment of Nokia Xpress for Lumia for Windows Phone 8 in a new Agile based methodology.
- Drove backlog for two development teams.
- Created a new UX/UI paradigm which allowed users to access their content faster.
- Worked with many offsite teams, including phone program management and application technical readiness, to secure
   Nokia Xpress as a mandatory preloaded application on Lumia devices.
- Launched Nokia Xpress on Lumia and acquired over half a million users in less than one year.

# **Senior Software Engineer**

**Nokia**, Itasca, Illinois February 2012 – May 2013

#### **Windows Phone**

- Prototyped and then led development of Nokia Xpress for Windows Phone. Prototype was developed in spare time with two other colleagues before being picked up for full time development.
- Developed main application architecture and led feature design.
- Led team in adopting Agile practices including moving to a DevOps model.

#### <u>Asha</u>

- Provided architecture guidance on all feature implementations as a senior member of the Web Apps platform team.
- Executed the ScrumMaster role while still also being an individual contributor on the team.
- Collaborated with Product Owner to define user stories.
- Promoted and participated in the first Nokia Browser team hackathon. Led a webinar introducing engineers to Web Apps. Contributed to a Web App game that won best hack.

# **Software Engineer**

**Nokia**, Itasca, Illinois July 2010 – February 2012

- Implemented a JavaScript library used for client-side manipulation.
- Created templates, samples and code snippets for the Nokia Web Tools product.
- Took on role of ScrumMaster for the S40 Web Apps team during our program's transition to Agile.
- Represented Xpress at Nokia World 2011 and participated in Nokia World Hackathon as a technical expert.
- Published, on my own time, two S40 Web Apps to the Nokia Store.

# **Adjunct Professor**

DeVry University, Addison, Illinois

November 2010 - May 2011

- Taught CIS-170C (Programming with Lab) with 20 students. Course content included introduction to C++ & Visual Studio, programming concepts, and a final project that demonstrated basic programming ability.
- Taught SEC-360 (Data Privacy and Security) with 7 students. Course content was focused around enterprise security including hardware, software, and security policies.

# **UI Software Engineer**

Novarra Inc. (Acquired by Nokia), Itasca, Illinois

October 2009 - June 2010

- Daily tasks included HTML, JavaScript, and PHP start page design and development.
- Created new server components to help achieve new start page features.
- Represented Novarra and won the Tech in the Middle Day of Mobile 2010 Hackathon. Created an Android on-device clipping program that interfaced with the Novarra Vision clipping product.

# **Quality Assurance/Development Intern**

**Novarra Inc.**, Itasca, Illinois June 2007 – October 2009

- Performance testing the Novarra Vision Server and Client product in both a manual and automated fashion.
- Managed and performed maintenance on the automated unit testing code using Java and Apache Ant.
- Led design and development of Vault, a Ruby on Rails application used to track test cases, test suites, and test results.

# **EDUCATION**

# Master of Business Administration with Concentration in Information Systems Management

Keller Graduate School of Management, Schaumburg, Illinois

GPA 3.75/4.0 (With Distinction)

March 2009 - October 2010

# Bachelor of Science, Computer Information Systems with Concentration in Computer Forensics

**DeVry University**, Addison, Illinois GPA 3.95/4.0 (Summa Cum Laude)

July 2006 - March 2009

# **AWARDS/ACHIEVEMENTS**

- Windy City Curling Club
  - o President August 2020 Present
  - Vice President June 2019 August 2020
  - Arena Nationals Men's Team 2019
- DeVry Chicago Metro Graduation Speaker, Addison Campus March 2009
- Boy Scouts of America Eagle Scout, Class of 2005

## **PATENTS**

- Method and Apparatus for Determining Partial Updates for a Document Object Model
  - United States 14/151472
  - o Filed January 9, 2014